Finding Aid for Pierson Family papers, 1821-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pierson Family papers 1821-1996
Pierson family.
1 oversize folders
8 linear feet
2010126 Aa 2; UAm
The Pierson Family papers cover the period between 1821 and 1996. Prominent members of the family include lawyer and politician Job Pierson (1791-1860) who served in Congress as a representative of New York from 1831 to 1835, and his son Reverend Job Pierson of Michigan. The collection is composed primarily of family correspondence, legal papers, genealogical research, newspaper clippings, printed materials, and visual materials, which include photographs, ambrotypes and daguerreotypes, tintypes, and ink drawings. The collection also contains materials documenting Clara Dillingham Pierson’s writing career as a children’s book author.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 2010 by Susan and Robert King and Jim and Polly Weaver (donor number 10325 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Job Pierson (1791-1860) was a lawyer and politician who served in Congress as a representative of New York from 1831 to 1835. He was born September 23, 1791 in Bridgehampton, New York and died April 9, 1860 in Troy, New York. He was the son of Samuel Pierson and Jerusha Conkling and a descendant of Henry Pierson, one of the early settlers of Southampton, Long Island. He graduate from Williams College in 1811 and went on to study law in Salem and Schaghticoke, New York. After being admitted to the bar in 1815, he began practicing law with Herman Knickerbocker in Rensselaer County, New York. Before being elected a member of the United States House of Representatives, he was district attorney in Rensselaer County, New York. After his time in Congress, he was elected Surrogate of Rensselaer County in 1835. He married Clarissa Taintor Bulkeley of Williamstown, Massachusetts on September 24, 1815. She was the daughter of Joshua Robbins Bulkeley and Sarah Bulkeley Taintor and a descendents of Rev. Peter Bulkeley, one of the founders of Concord, Massachusetts.
Job and Clarissa Pierson had five children, Sarah Jerusha (1816-1866), Samuel Dayton (1819-1850), Job (1824-1896), Mary Bulkeley (1825-1851), and John Bulkeley (1828-1885). Sarah Jerusha Pierson married Philip Titus Heartt in 1839 and had 8 children. Mary Bulkeley Pierson married Major Oscar F. Winship in 1854 and had one child. John Bulkeley Pierson was married to Mary Lockwood until her death. He was married for a second time to Harriet L. VanSchoonhoven.
Rev. Job Pierson (1824-1896) was born in Schaghticoke, New York on February 3, 1824 and died on February 3, 1896 in Stanton, Michigan. He graduated from Williams College in 1842 and then from Auburn Theological Seminary in 1847. Rev. Job Pierson was pastor of the First Presbyterian Church in Pittsford, New York from 1850 to 1856. Later, he was pastor in Victor, New York from 1856 to 1863; Kalamazoo, Michigan from 1863 to 1868; and in Ionia, Michigan from 1868 to 1878. In 1878, he retired from active ministry and spent the remainder of his life in literary pursuits such as contributing to the Oxford Philological Society's New English Dictionary. He was also briefly the Librarian of Alma College in Alma, Michigan.
Rev. Job Pierson married Rachel Williams Smith of Geneva, New York on February 7, 1849. The couple had five children, Clarissa Taintor (1850-1889), Samuel Dayton (b. 1852), John Williams Smith (1854-1946), Bowen Whiting (b. 1858) and Philip Titus Heartt (1859). Clarissa Pierson married Beverly Chew of New York in 1811. The couple had no children. Bowen Whiting Pierson married Nannie Meach of Norwich, Connecticut and had one child, Clarissa Pierson (1890-1974).
John Williams Smith Pierson was born in Pittford, New York July 20, 1854. He was a merchant in Stanton, Michigan, opening his first Hardware store in 1878 with the assistance of his brother Philip T. H. Pierson. He continued his hardware business until 1908. In 1911, he established The John W.S. Pierson Company and began selling investment securities. John W.S. Pierson married Clara Dillingham of Coldwater, Michigan on October 9, 1894. The couple had one biological child, John Lincoln who was born January 30, 1900. However, he died five days later on February 4, 1900. They adopted two sons, first John Howard Pierson, and later Harold Dillingham. John Howard Pierson married Carrie Louise and had two daughters, Eleanor and Maxine.
Clara Dillingham Pierson was born March 11, 1868 in Coldwater, Michigan. She was the only child of Captain Lucius Abell Dillingham and Jennie Lincoln. She was primarily schooled at home by her mother, but did graduate from a kindergarten training program in Chicago. Before her marriage to John W.S. Pierson in 1894, she taught a two-year kindergarten-training course at Alma College. After her marriage, she began writing for and about children. Her books were published by E.P. Dutton & Co. and include, among others, her nature stories for children: Among the Meadow People (1897), Among the Forest People, (1898), Among the Farm-Yard People (1899), and Among the Pond People (1901). Clara D. Pierson moved to Grand Rapids in 1930 with her husband John and lived there until her death in 1952.
The Pierson Family papers cover the period between 1821 and 1996. The collection is composed primarily of family correspondence, legal papers, genealogical research, newspaper clippings, printed materials, and visual materials, which include photographs, ambrotypes and daguerreotypes, tintypes, and ink drawings. The collection also contains materials documenting Clara E. Dillingham Pierson's writing career as a children's book author.
The collection has been arranged into four principal series: Family Groups, Clara E. D. Pierson (1868-1952) Papers, Visual Materials, and Other Materials.
Subjects:
Authors, American.; Children's authors.; Children's literature.; Clergy--Michigan.; Coldwater (Mich.); Nature stories.; Pierson, Bowen Whiting.; Pierson, Clara Dillingham.; Pearson family.; Pierson, Job, 1791-1860.; Pierson, Job, 1824-1896.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan.; Stanton (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings--Michigan.; Dwellings--New York (State); Omena (Mich.); Pearson family.; Pierson, Bowen Whiting.; Pierson, Clara Dillingham.; Pierson, Job, 1824-1896.; Stanton (Mich.); Suffolk County (N.Y.)
Genre Terms:
Ambrotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Mourning jewelry.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Tintypes.
- Family Groups
  The series Family Groups covers 170 years of the Pierson Family and consists of family correspondence, legal papers, genealogical research, and newspaper clippings. The series has been arranged by generation, which is subdivided by Personal Name. Each generation has been made into its own sub-series. The sub-series First Generation contains papers of lawyer and politician Job Pierson (1791-1860), which include formal dinner invitations, cemetery deed, certificate to practice law in New York, and biographical material post dating his death. The sub-series Second Generation contains the papers of the children of Job Pierson (1791-1860) and his wife Clarissa Taintor Bulkeley. While Job and Clarissa Pierson had five children, only two, Job Pierson (1824-1896) and John Bulkeley Pierson (1828-1885) are represented in this series. The papers of Reverend Job Pierson include his heavily annotated bible, correspondence, a photocopied version of his diary, legal and financial papers, and biographical material post dating his death. Job Pierson's correspondence includes communications between himself and family members as well as correspondences from Nathaniel and Frank Topping dealing with various financial and legal matters. The sub-series also contains the papers of Job Pierson's wife Rachel Williams Smith. The sub-series Third Generation contains the papers of the children of Job and Rachel Pierson. The Fourth Generation and Fifth Generation sub-series represent the grandchildren and great-grandchildren of Reverend Job Pierson accordingly. The series also contains the sub-series Other Families. This sub-series is made up of genealogical research on families related to the Pierson family.
  - First Generation
    - Job Pierson (1791-1860)
      - Biographical Material 1821-1981 (Box 1)
        (includes biographical material post dating his death)
  - Second Generation
    - Job Pierson (1824-1896)
      - Bible 1840 (Box 1)
        (The English version of the Polyglot Bible containing the Old and New Testaments, with a copious and original selection of references to parallel and illustrative passages, exhibited in a manner hitherto unattempted: facsimile large edition [of the English version of Bagster's Polyglot Bible])
      - Correspondence
        - General 1847-1896, 2 folders (Box 1)
        - Nathaniel and Frank A. Topping 1860-1911 (Box 1)
      - Diary, 1850-1895 (Box 1)
        (copy of original)
      - Legal and Financial Papers 1870s-1890s (Box 1)
      - Other Papers 1890s-1910s, 1970s (Box 1)
    - Rachel Williams Smith Pierson (1820-1908) (wife of Job Pierson) 1878-1931 (Box 1)
    - John Bulkeley Pierson (1828-1885)
      - Correspondence 1861-1894 (Box 1)
      - Legal Papers 1870s-1880s (Box 1)
  - Third Generation
    - Beverly Chew (husband of Clarissa Taintor Pierson) 1875-1916 (Box 1)
    - Samuel Dayton Pierson (b. 1852) 1886-1914 (Box 1)
    - John William Stratton Pierson (1854-1946)
      - Correspondence 1880s-1930s (Box 1)
      - Legal and Financial Papers 1882-1932 (Box 1)
      - Library Catalogue (Box 1)
      - Other Papers 1880-1932 (Box 1)
        (includes newspaper clippings, biographical material, and other papers from the John W.S. Pierson Hardware Establishment)
    - Bowen Whiting Pierson (b. 1858)
      - Biographical Sketch and Personal Library Catalogue 1907-1908 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1891-1921 (Box 1)
      - Genealogical Research 1891-1901 (Box 1)
    - Philip T.H. Pierson (b. 1859) 1880s-1910s, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Fourth Generation
    - Clarissa Pierson Jacocks (daughter of Bowen Whiting and Nannie Pierson)
      - Correspondence 1928-1974 (Box 1)
      - Legal Papers 1960s-1970s (Box 1)
    - John Howard Pierson (son of John William Smith and Clara Pierson) 1904-1947 (Box 1)
    - Carrie Louise Pierson (wife of John Howard Pierson) 1930s-1970s (Box 1)
  - Fifth Generation
    - Eleanor W. Pierson Porter (daughter of John Howard and Carrie Louise Pierson) 1927, 1975, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Other Families
    - Buckley Family circa 1880s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Chisebaugh Family undated (Box 2)
    - Conkling Family circa 1890s (Box 2)
    - Dayton Family undated (Box 2)
    - Drury-Comins Family undated (Box 2)
    - Pindar, Pyndar, and Pinder family undated (Box 2)
    - Smith Family circa 1900s-1970s (Box 2)
    - Stratton Family undated (Box 2)
- Clara Dillingham Pierson (1868-1952) Papers
  The series Clara D. Pierson (1868-1952) Papers documents the life and activities of Clara Dillingham Pierson, the wife of Reverend Job Pierson's son John W.S. Pierson. The series consists chiefly of letters written by Clara to her mother Jennie Lincoln Dillingham between 1887 and 1910. The letters describe the daily activities and major events in Clara's life from her days as a student in Chicago and teacher at Alma College, to her courtship and subsequent marriage to John W.S. Pierson, the couple's life in Stanton, Michigan and later, the adoption of their sons John Howard and Harold Pierson. Clara D. Pierson has written on some of the envelopes describing the contents of the letters. For example, on the envelope of a letter from May 1888, Clara D. Pierson has written, "These [letters] from Ann Arbor where I relocated for the Commencement rush sound pretty frivolous but it was all clean fun and every one of the young men mentioned would have been glad to introduce me to the girl he married later." Other papers in this series include drafts and published versions of Clara D. Pierson's writings, correspondence with various friends and family members, genealogical research, newspaper clippings, legal and financial papers, and Clara D. Pierson's autobiography.
  - Alma College 1894, 1896 (Box 2)
    (includes programs and commencement speech given by Clara D. Pierson)
  - Autobiography undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with
    - Dillingham, Jennie L.
      - July 1887-December 1894, 14 folders (Box 2)
      - January 1895-December 1902, 19 folders (Box 3)
      - January 1903-April 1909, 16 folders (Box 4)
      - May 1909-May 1910 undated (Box 5)
    - Dutton, Edward Payson 1903-1920, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Friends and relatives 1878-1952, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Pierson, John Williams Smith 1893-1894, 1944, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Dillingham Genealogy 1920s (Box 5)
  - Dillingham, Jennie Lincoln (1839-1916)
    (Clara's mother)
    - Correspondence 1870s-1910s (Box 5)
    - Marriage License 1865 (Box 5)
    - Obituary 1916 (Box 5)
  - Dutton, Edward Payson, newspaper clippings and death announcement 1923 (Box 5)
  - E.P. Dutton & Co., account statements 1909-1954 (Box 5)
  - Heston, Winfred E. 1908-1937 (Box 5)
    (Alma College alumna and surgeon who worked in India)
  - Journal Entries 1892, 1933, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Last Will and Testament 1949 (Box 5)
  - Lecture on the Health of Teachers (Box 5)
  - Lincoln, Edwin Augustus 1848, 1992 (Box 5)
    (includes newspaper death announcement and correspondence from Eleanor E. Porter regarding E.A. Lincoln's portrait)
  - Lincoln Genealogy undated (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1900s-1960s (Box 5)
  - Obituary 1952 (Box 5)
  - Omena, Michigan (writings and ephemera) 1899-1923 (Box 5)
  - Personal Account Book 1894 (Box 5)
  - Personal Account Book 1947 (Box 5)
  - Ring belonging to Sherlock H. Lincoln (great uncle of Clara D. Pierson) circa 1820s (Box 5)
  - Writings
    - Articles and short essays, circa 1900s-1930s, 3 folders
      - "Aurora" (Box 5)
      - "Authorship as a Vocation" (Box 5)
      - "A Bargain in Happiness" (Box 5)
      - "Benny Gorham's Lovely Day" (Box 5)
      - "The Child in the Midst" (Box 5)
      - "Concerning Roads" (Box 5)
      - "Consolations of a Gardenless Gardener" (Box 5)
      - "Endless Quests" (Box 5)
      - "Every-day Blossoms" (Box 5)
      - "The Evolution of Surgery" (Box 5)
      - "The Evolution of the Edition" (Box 5)
      - "Faith and a Henhouse" (Box 5)
      - "A Five Days Parting" (Box 5)
      - "The Happiness in Writing for Children" (Box 5)
      - "Hawaii" (Box 5)
      - "Heirloom Histories" (Box 5)
        (documents the history of the Dillingham and Lincoln family heirlooms)
      - "Heredity versus Environment" (Box 5)
      - "Home-made Onion Flavoring" (Box 5)
      - "How to Correspond without Writing" (Box 5)
      - "How to Plan Your Own Service Quarters" (Box 5)
      - "The Indignant Clothing" (Box 5)
      - "Interruptions" (Box 5)
      - "The Marauding Grackle" (Box 5)
      - "The Mother of an Angel" (Box 5)
      - "Mr. Nilsson" (Box 5)
      - "A New Way of Keeping Tablecloths" (Box 5)
      - "The Primary Teacher in the Country Sunday-School" (Box 5)
      - "Problems in Natural History" (Box 5)
      - "Quakers in the United States" (Box 5)
      - "Some of the Best Writers of Nature Books for Children" (Box 5)
      - "A Thanksgiving Ritual" (Box 5)
      - "Ways that are dark" (Box 5)
      - "When one is ill" (Box 5)
      - "Were there any Colonial Authors?" (Box 5)
      - "U.S. Copyright Law and Our Relation to it" (Box 5)
      - "Utilizing Existing Agencies" (Box 5)
    - Books
      - Among the Meadow People, 1897 (Box 6)
      - Among the Forest People, 1898 (Box 6)
      - Among the Farm-Yard People, 1899 (Box 6)
      - Among the Pond People, 1901 (Box 6)
      - Living with our Children, 1923 (Box 6)
      - Dr. Miss Doctor, undated (Box 6)
    - Poetry, circa 1900s-1930s (Box 6)
  - Untitled Drafts and Notes, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series complements the manuscript and printed materials contained in the collection's other series. The visual materials include ambrotypes and daguerreotypes, ink drawings, photographs, prints, postcards, and tintypes. Most of the Pierson Family photographs are formal portraits rather than casual snapshots of various members of the Pierson family. Additionally, the series contains photographs of various houses owned by Pierson family members. The Pierson Family farmhouse located in Long Island, New York is thoroughly documented as there was an album containing a photograph of every room in that house.
  - Ambrotypes and Daguerreotypes
    - Edwin Augustus Lincoln circa 1850s, 2 items (Box 6)
    - Jennie Lincoln at age 10 and 12 circa 1950s, 3 items (Box 6)
    - Mother of Edwin Augustus Lincoln circa 1850s (Box 6)
    - Mother of Amanda Drury Lincoln circa 1850s (Box 6)
    - Unidentified family, man, woman and female child circa 1850s (Box 7)
    - Unidentified family, four individual portraits of a mother, father, son and daughter circa 1850s (Box 7)
    - Unidentified man circa 1850s (Box 7)
    - Two unidentified women with a book circa 1850s (Box 7)
  - Drawing
    - Interior View of J.W. Smith & Co.'s Store (Geneva, NY) undated (Box 7)
    - John W.S. Pierson Hardware Establishment undated (Box 7)
    - John W.S. Pierson in his Stanton home study undated (Folder 1)
  - Encased painting of Jennie Lincoln circa 1860s (Box 7)
  - Encased mourning jewelry with painting of an unidentified man, circa 1860s (Box 7)
    (also includes weaved hairs and a photograph of a man holding a child)
  - Photocopy of Pierson Family Crest undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    - Beverly Place, retirement home of Job Pierson (Stanton, Mich.) circa 1890s (Box 7)
    - Bradley, Dan Freeman circa 1930s (Box 7)
    - Buckley Wells as a young boy with a violin 1881 (Box 7)
    - Dillingham Home (Coldwater, Mich.) undated (Box 7)
    - Dutton, Edward Payson circa 1890s (Box 7)
    - Drury Comins Family circa 1870s-1890s (Box 7)
    - Hobart Whitaker Family circa 1890s-1940s (Box 7)
    - Library of Congress "My Dear Wife" Exhibit (Box 7)
    - Lincoln Family Home (Plainfield, Massachusetts) undated (Folder 1)
      (Photograph has been removed from original frame. Clara D. Pierson had written on the back of the frame about the origin of the house and who should take possession of the photograph. A photocopy of what she wrote is contained in the oversize folder)
    - John W.S, Pierson Family Home (Stanton, Mich.) circa 1910s (Box 7)
    - Pierson Family
      - Second Generation
        - Lucius A. Dillingham circa 1860s-1880s (Box 7)
        - Rachel Williams Smith Pierson circa 1890s (Box 7)
        - Jennie Lincoln Dillingham circa 1860s-1890s (Box 7)
        - Job Pierson circa 1870s (Box 7)
      - Third Generation
        - Bowen Whiting Pierson circa 1890s (Box 7)
        - Clara and John Pierson circa 1920s-1930s (Box 7)
        - Clara Eleanor Dillingham Pierson 1870s-1920s (Box 7)
        - Clarissa Pierson Chew circa 1880s (Box 7)
        - John W. S. Pierson 1860s-1870s, 1920s-1930s (Box 7)
        - Nannie Meach Pierson (wife of Bowen Whiting Pierson) circa 1890s (Box 7)
        - Philip T. H. Pierson 1860s-1880s (Box 7)
        - Samuel Pierson circa 1890s (Box 7)
      - Fourth Generation
        - Clarissa Pierson Jacocks (daughter of Bowen Whiting and Nannie Meach Pierson) 1890s-1910s, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Pierson Family Group circa 1870s-1890s (Box 7)
    - Pierson Farmhouse (Long Island, NY) undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (Photographs in folder 1 have been removed from an album and photographs in folder 2 have been removed from their frame. Clara D. Pierson had written on the back of the frame. A photocopy of what she wrote is contained in folder 2)
    - Pierson House (Geneva, NY) 1870s (Box 7)
    - Portraits and Misc. Family Portraits 1870s-1970s (Box 7)
    - Omena, Michigan 1910s-1940s (Box 7)
    - Stanton, Michigan circa 1900s (Box 7)
    - Unidentified Houses and Churches circa 1870s-1880s (Box 7)
  - Postcards
    - Stanton, Michigan (Box 7)
    - Misc. Michigan circa 1900s (Box 7)
    - Warren, Mass. undated (Box 7)
  - Prints
    - Abraham Lincoln undated (Box 8)
    - Lieutenant General Grant undated (Box 8)
    - Colonel Elmer E. Ellsworth undated (Box 8)
  - Tintypes
    - Unidentified female child circa 1880s, 2 tintypes (Box 8)
    - Unidentified man, possibly Samuel Dayton Pierson circa 1880s (Box 8)
    - John W. S. Pierson circa 1880s (Box 8)
    - Bowen Whiting Pierson at Military School circa 1870s (Box 8)
  - Watercolor, Portrait of Clarrisa Pierson Chew circa 1880s (Box 8)
- Other Materials
  The Other Materials series contains miscellaneous material not related to a specific Pierson family member. The series is made up of printed materials, newspaper clippings, genealogical research on the Pierson family, legal and financial papers, and other assorted miscellanea. There is a significant amount of material related to the Pierson family farmhouse located in Long Island, New York. This material primarily consists of legal correspondence, land deeds, and other financial materials regarding the home and property in New York.
  - 1781 Carolus dollar and 1853 half dime, 1781, 1853 (Box 8)
  - Centennial of the First Presbyterian Church of Ionia, Michigan 1942 (Box 8)
  - Chronology of the Pierson Family 1864 (Box 8)
    (written by Rev. Job Pierson)
  - Coldwater, Michigan 1885-1960 (Box 8)
  - Confederate 50 dollar bill 1865 (Box 8)
  - Genealogy Notebook of Related Families undated (Box 8)
  - Library of Congress 1991-1996 (Box 8)
  - Lincoln Calendar 1908 (Box 8)
  - Long Island Property 1840s-1970s, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Abraham Lincoln 1960s-1990s (Box 8)
    - Distantly Related Family 1900s-1940s (Box 8)
    - Michigan 1900s-1960s (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous 1900s-1960s (Box 8)
  - Pierson Family Genealogy 1890s-1990s, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Printed Materials
    - Central Montcalm Historical Society: Bicentennial Edition, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Authors Association Grand Rapids Meeting 1927 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Library Bulletin 1926 (Box 8)
    - The Rolfe Property: Warren House at "Smith's Fort Plantation" 1652-1935, 1935 (Box 8)
    - Snow Bound, John Greenleaf Whittier, 1900 (Box 8)
    - Stanton Centennial, 1963 (Box 8)
    - The Story of Leelanau, Julia Terry Dickinson, 1951 (Box 8)
    - A Tour of Historic Sag Harbour, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Map of Property owned by John Howard and Carrie Louise Pierson (Sagaponack, NY) 1963 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Legal and Financial Papers 1860s-1930s (Box 8)
  - Stamp Collection (Box 8)
  - Stanton Household Inventory 1929-1930 (Box 8)
Related Material
Researchers interested in the Pierson Family should also consult the Job Pierson Family Papers located in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress. These materials primarily relate to lawyer and politician Job Pierson (1791-1860).